Guide to the James T. Sears Papers, 1918-2011 and undated, bulk 1950-2004 RL.01162
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Research and Writings, 1941-2007 and undated, bulk 1975-2005, 176 boxes
  - Other Publications Subseries, 1984-2007
    - Teaching and Thinking about Curriculum: Critical Inquiries (1990), 1987-1990 and undated, 3 boxes
      Edited by Sears and J. Dan Marshall; reprinted in 2001. Files house correspondence, editorial files, reviews, and routine administrative files. Correspondence includes exchanges with Teachers College Press and prospective authors. Editorial files only include those abstracts and drafts that Sears accepted for publication. Reviews are organized by number; all other folders are organized alphabetically.
      - Correspondence, 1987-1990, 6 folders (Box 225)
      - Editorial files, 1988-1989, 20 folders (Box 226)
      - Reviews, 1987-1988 and undated, 11 folders (Box 227)
      - Administrative files, 1987-1988 and undated, 8 folders (Box 227)
    - Turning Points in Curriculum: A Contemporary American Memoir (2000 and 2002), 1992-2002 and undated, 2 boxes
      Arranged in three groups: correspondence, drafts and proofs, and publicity. Files relate to 2000 and 2002 editions of this anthology. Correspondence consists of exchanges between some of the authors (Louise Allen, James Sears, J. Dan Marshall, Patrick Roberts, and William A. Schubert) and the publishers. Loose drafts and publisher revisions are often included with this correspondence. The Drafts and Proofs grouping houses copy edits, drafts, layouts, and manuscripts.
      - Correspondence, 1992-2002, 5 folders (Box 228)
      - Drafts and proofs, 1994-2002 and undated, 6 folders (Box 228)
      - Drafts and proofs, 1994-2002 and undated, 9 folders (Box 229)
      - Publicity files, 2000 (Box 229)
    - When Best Doesn't Equal Good: Educational Reform and Teacher Recruitment. A Longitudinal Study (1994), 1989-1993 and undated
      Six-year study Edited by Sears and other authors, focusing on the Bridenthal Internship in Teaching program at Central College, Iowa, later known as the Breckenridge (BIT). Other materials on BIT are located in the Professional Papers Series, Teaching Subseries.
      - FIles (Box 229)
    - Youth, Education and Sexualities (2006), 2002-2005, 4 boxes
      - Contributor files (Box 230-232)
      - Correspondence, 2003-2005, 7 folders (Box 233)
      - Various administrative files, 2003-2005, 14 folders (Box 233)
  - Research Files Subseries, 1924-1999 and undated, 25 boxes
    Materials covering a wide variety of research topics of interest to Sears, including homosexuality in the United States before 1950, the history of gays in the military, a study on new generations of gays, and international gay movements. Other boxes contain general research materials on gays in the South which informed multiple works by Sears. The individual states of Alabama and Florida have their own boxes of research materials, while materials from Arkansas, Georgia, Louisiana, Kentucky, North Carolina, Tennessee, Texas, and Washington D.C. are housed as a group. Formats in the Research Files Subseries are varied, and can include print materials such as clippings, flyers, newsletters, and serial issues; field notes and other research materials; correspondence; photographs and other types of illustrations; and recorded oral histories and interviews. In addition to correspondence and materials deriving from Sears' research, there are significant amounts of primary materials from original sources, especially correspondence and a few diaries. More detailed descriptions follow below.
    - Alabama Files, 1971-1998 and undated, 2 boxes
      Research files contain clippings, articles, writings by others, flyers, organizations' records, and notes on homosexuality and the gay rights movement in Alabama, with emphasis on Birmingham, AIDS, gay movement organizations, and institutional reactions to the increasingly visible and active gay movement. Also includes a set of essays (1995-1997) written by Patrick Cather for the Alabama Forum, a monthly gay newsletter. Materials were used extensively for Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones. Arranged in original order as received.
      - Research files, 1971-1998 and undated (Box 234-235)
    - Early Gay History, 1920s-1999 and undated (bulk 1930s-1940s), 3 boxes
      Research materials concerning three individuals interviewed by Sears: Jeri Farrar of Lewiston, Maine, Julian "Jerry" Hayes of South Carolina, and Perry Schwartz of South Carolina. Formats include interviews on cassettes (removed to the Audiovisual Series), photographs, many folders of correspondence, memoirs, and a diary.
      The undated Farrar memoir covers the years 1932-circa 1945 and narrates events in the life of Farrar, her close friend and musical collaborator Rena Estabrooks, Farrar's mother Edna, and various friends, male and female; there are references to World War II and social conditions of the times, and detailed descriptions of nightclub circuits and the entertainment business in New York and New Jersey. It was probably written in the 1980s or 1990s.
      The Hayes materials offer a detailed look into the life of a gay man growing up in rural North Carolina who "came out" in college and became part of the early gay community in Charleston, South Carolina during the 1940s. Materials include a diary kept in Jerry Hayes' teen years (typed transcription), a brief memoir by Hayes, interviews conducted in 1999, and paper prints of digitized photographs that date from circa 1920-1940.
      The Schwartz materials cover the life events of a gay man from Birmingham, Alabama, who also became a Charleston resident; the bulk of this material consists of photocopies of hundreds of pieces of correspondence, numbered and arranged in chronological order, from Schwartz to family members and friends during his military service, 1936-1946. Includes interviews on cassettes conducted in 1998. A few folders contain early printed matter from 1957-1966, including a pamphlet on the psychology of homosexuality, and a "gay girl's guide."
      Finally, another set of files corresponds to research Sears conducted on early criminal cases linked with homosexual behavior, and personal histories of lesbians in the Northeast during the early 20th centuries (Laura Beam, Harriet Hosmer, Ellen Day Hale), and contain resource listings from the Schlesinger Library at Harvard and some photocopied primary material from several archival institutions, including Duke University.
      [Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use and have been removed to the Audiovisual Materials Series (boxes 22-23). Technical Services staff must arrange to have use copies made before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use these materials.]
      - Jeri Farrar memoir and other material, 1999 and undated (Box 236)
      - Julian "Jerry" Hayes correspondence, diaries, and photographs, 1920s-1999 and undated, bulk 1930s-1940s (Box 236)
      - Perry Schwartz correspondence, 1936-1998 and undated, bulk 1936-1946 (Box 237-238)
      - Other research files, 1924-1995 (early dates refer to historical content of photocopied archival material), 7 folders (Box 238)
    - Florida Files, 1954-1996, undated, 2 boxes
      Chiefly clippings and some correspondence and printed material related to gay history, civil rights, and the social and political scene in Florida from the mid-1950s through the early 1980s. Includes a correspondence file for the Florida Mattachine Society; individuals of note here include Richard Inman, Jack Nichols, and Leonard Matlovich (materials on these individuals also appear in other series of the collection). Other materials document the nascent gay rights movement on university campuses and in major Florida cities, as well as actions by law enforcement and government bodies to counter it. Materials on Anita Bryant's anti-homosexual activism are found here. Other files relate to the social scene of Florida clubs and discos. Publications by the Florida gay community as well as mainstream newspapers are included. Some large clippings have been moved to Oversize Material. Oral histories and interviews on cassettes can be found in the Audiovisual Materials Series. Files are in original order as received.
      - Research files, 1954-1996 and undated (Box 239-240)
    - Gays in the Military Research Files, 1947-1998 and undated, bulk 1970s, 1 box
      Documentation about several legal cases targeting gay individuals serving in the U.S. military, as well as more general research materials on gays in the military. Files include court and military papers as well as many news articles and clippings, and first-person accounts.
      - Research files, 1947-1998 and undated (Box 241)
    - International Research Material, 1991-2006 and undated, 2 boxes
      Chiefly printed reports, newsletters, and other publications collected by Sears, relating to gay movements and sexual identity issues in these countries: Canada, China, Ireland (two folders), Japan (four folders), Israel, New Zealand, the United Kingdom (England, Scotland, Ireland), and the United States.
      - Canada-Ireland, 2005-2006 (Box 241)
      - Japan-U.S., 1991-2006 (Box 242)
    - Next Generation Research Files, 1977-1998 and undated, 1 box
      Correspondence, printed materials, organization files, notes, recorded interviews, and photographs related to Sears' planned volume on gay history focusing on "Gen X" lesbians, gays, and transgender individuals born in the 1970s and 1980s. Printed materials include clippings, newspapers, flyers, and articles. Topics with significant amounts of material in these research files include gay youth and AIDS, same-sex sexual harassment, and gay communities in Florida. One set of files follows the case of Pedro Zamora, gay activist who died of AIDS at age 22, especially focusing on media coverage of his life and death; another set of research materials documents the "Enloe Six" case in N.C., and includes original correspondence with one of the young men involved in the case. Material has not been published. Finally, there are three videos: one covering the memorial service for Zamora, another about the media coverage of the "Enloe Six." A third contains unknown material, possibly on AIDS as presented through Hollywood productions. Arranged in original order as received.
      [Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Technical Services staff need to produce use copies before contents can be accessed. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use these materials.]
      - Research files, 1977-1998 (Box 243)
    - Philippines Study, 1999 and undated, 2 boxes
      Materials gathered during Fulbright Award study undertaken by Sears of sexuality and community in the Philippines. Portions of this work appeared in A Dangerous Knowing.
      - Ladlad Project, Chapter 1 prospectus (Box 244)
      - Los Gigantes, circa 1997 (unpublished essay) (Box 244)
      - Notebooks, 2 folders (Box 244)
      - Photographs, 7 folders (Box 244)
      - Postcards, blank, Manila Hotel (Box 244)
      - Slides, images from ceremony (Box 244)
      - Slides, 2 folders (Box 244)
      - Negatives, 23 folders (Box 245)
    - Printed Material Research Files, 1954-2004 and undated, 2 boxes
      Scholarly journals, gay magazines, gay directories and guides from various cities, clippings, and other printed materials gathered as research for various projects. Arranged alphabetically by title or topic. Many other printed items are found throughout the Sears Papers, especially clippings, articles, and newsletters; entire issues of serials are housed in the Oversize Material boxes.
      - Ariadne-Der Kreis, 10 folders (Box 246)
      - UpFront-Wiggins newspaper articles, 6 folders (Box 247)
    - Sex Education Community Studies, 1976-1993 and undated, 3 boxes
      Contains clippings, correspondence, field notes, photographic material, recorded interviews, and printed materials used in Sears' research on sex education curricula in the U.S. Arranged by geographical area of research: Illinois, North Carolina, and South Carolina, with separate files for negatives and photographs. Field notebooks are organized by schools visited. Fifty audiocassettes of interviews have been housed separately in the Audiovisual Material Series.
      - Chicago, Illinois (Box 248)
        Clippings, correspondence, field notes, photos, and other research material. Chicago schools visited by Sears include Arai, Coleman, Dyett, and Eli Whitney.
      - Winnetka, Illinois (Box 248)
        Contains mostly field notes; also contains some correspondence, photographs, and printed materials.
      - Photographs, 2 folders (Box 249)
        Black-and-white and color photographs from Chicago, Winnetka and South Carolina. Material depicted includes Eli Whitney and Washburne schools, as well as a South Carolina gay and lesbian pride march.
      - Negatives, Chicago and South Carolina (Box 249)
        Arrangement note
        Corresponds with the second photographs folder.
      - North Carolina files (Box 249)
        Contains clippings, correspondence, educational pamphlets and writings from Cherokee, North Carolina. Includes materials which may have been used on the work Out of Harmony on the Cherokee Boundary. There are also several drafts of the Keetowah essay.
      - South Carolina files, 3 folders (Box 249)
        Contains clippings, field notes, and a copy of Cultural Wars in a Southern Town: Race and the Hidden Narrative of the Master, the article resulting from this regional study. Most papers relate to the contentious debate over sex education in Beaufort, S.C. Sears' study of this case was to be the basis for a book. Additional material pertaining to the Gullah community at St. Helena Island, and the Penn School is also included. Bulk of files in box 250.
      - Unidentified field notes (Box 249)
      - Unidentified negatives (Box 249)
      - South Carolina files on Beaufort "3R" controversy. Also, a folder of material on a similar controversy at St. John's Episcopal School in California (1994). (Box 250)
    - Southern States Research Files, 1979-2000 and undated, 2 boxes
      Assembled by Sears, these materials document homosexuality and the gay movement of the 1970s-1990s in Arkansas, Georgia, Louisiana, Kentucky, North Carolina, Tennessee, and Texas, and Washington DC. Similar in content to other state files found in the Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones series, formats include clippings, flyers, brochures, organizations' records, publications (newsletters), articles, and some correspondence. One set of folders relates to two national gay rights marches in Washington, D.C. in 1979 and 1987, and contains publicity and correspondence sent to Sears from organizers reminiscing about the earlier march. Other files house an extensive collection of newspapers that chronicle gay rights protests in Durham/Chapel Hill area of North Carolina. Also includes a set of files chronicling the Southeastern Conferences for Lesbians and Gay Men (1976-1990). In original order as received.
      - Research files, 1979-2000 and undated (Box 251-252)
  - Research Permissions Subseries, 1987-2000, 1 box
    Signed consent forms from individuals featured chiefly in Lonely Hunters and Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones, giving permission for their image or personal histories and interviews to be published by Sears. Other series in the Sears Papers house additional consent forms for the same or other published works. Researchers wishing to publish information on individuals represented in the Sears Papers must locate the consent forms, or obtain permission from the individuals.
    - Informed consent forms, 1987-1999 (Box 253)
    - Photographic permissions, 1995-2000 (Box 253)
  - Writings by Others Subseries, 1989-2005, 2 boxes
    Drafts of published and unpublished writings by other authors, chiefly on gender identity or sexual orientation and teaching, submitted to Sears for review, usually with some correspondence included. Organized alphabetically by author name.
    - Cohen, Stephan, An Historical Investigation of School and Community-Based Gay Liberation Youth Groups, New York City, 1969-1975: 'An Army of Lovers Cannot Fail' (PhD thesis, Harvard University), 2006 (Box 288)
    - Kissen, Rita (ed.), Getting Ready for Benjamin... (2004), 2000 and undated (Box 288)
    - Macgillivray, Ian, Sexual Orientation and School Policy (2004), 2001-2002 and undated (Box 288)
    - Miller, John, translation of Colombian writer Fernando Molanos Vargas' Un beso de Dick, titled "Dick's Kiss" (sample), 2004-2005 (Box 289)
    - Morris, Rosalind C., Three Sexes and Four Sexualities: Redressing the Discourses on Gender and Sexuality in Contemporary Thailand (1994), 2001-2002 and undated (Box 289)
    - Proctor, Keryn (Kerry), Breaking Through: A Whole-School Approach, Building Safer School Cultures and Greater Acceptance of Sexual Diversity (PhD thesis, La Trobe University, Australia), 2006 Apr. (Box 289)
    - Rutgers University, In Every Classroom: The Report of the President's Select Committee for Lesbian and Gay Concerns (1989), 1989 (Box 289)
      Sent to Sears to be reviewed in Empathy
    - Teal, Donn, If I Should Die Before I Wake, unpublished novella, 2003-2004 (Box 289)
- Jack Nichols Papers, 1940-2005 and undated, 34 boxes
  Collection of writings, ephemera, clippings, and other materials assembled by Jack Nichols, close friend of James Sears. The two met in the 1970s while Sears was researching the first volume in his series on gay history. Nichols, a journalist, writer, and gay activist from the sixties, became one of Sears' primary contributors to Lonely Hunters and to subsequent historical works by Sears, most notably Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones. When Nichols died of complications from AIDS in 2005, he bequeathed his personal papers to Sears. The papers have been kept in original order and are arranged in the following subseries: Clippings and Printed Materials; Correspondence; Personal Files; Serials; Subject Files; Writings; and Oversize Material. Audiovisual documentary materials relating to the life of Jack Nichols originally part of his personal papers and separated due to preservation needs are found in the photographs, audio and video recordings in the Audiovisual Material Series of the Sears Papers; many additional files pertaining to Nichols are in the subseries for Rebels, Rubyfruit, and Rhinestones in the Research and Writings Series, and a smaller amount of materials are in the Research Files Subseries of the Research and Writings Series..
  - Nichols Clippings and Printed Material, 1969-2004 and undated, 3 boxes
    Comprised almost entirely of newspaper and magazine clippings highlighting Nichols' work as a social activist and writer as well as various movements of interest to him. Included in this series are clippings of coverage of gay rights demonstrations, often related to government responses to the AIDS crisis. Several books of clippings (one with photographs) document Nichols' activities as a gay rights organizer in the cities of Washington, New York, and Cocoa Beach, Florida. In addition, clippings and printed materials related to "men's liberation" and related critiques of traditional gender roles can be found in this series. Copies of some writings by Nichols, notably the serialized Calamus Chronicles (originally The Tomcat Chronicles), as well as some clippings of articles and editorials written for Florida newspapers are housed in this series. Organized alphabetically.
    Separated Materials note
    [Some items removed to Oversize Material.]
    - The Advocate, Florida Today clippings, 1975, 1996 (Box 254)
    - Article clippings, undated (Box 254)
    - Bulletin board cards and clippings, undated (Box 254)
    - Carter, Logan LA Times article and other clippings, 1983, 1990, undated (Box 254)
    - Clipping books, 1986-1996, 1-2 of 8 folders (Box 254)
    - Clipping books, 1986-1996, 3-8 of 8 folders (Box 254)
    - Clippings and printed material, 1969-1996, 2 folders (Box 254)
    - Clippings and reviews, 1972-1997 (Box 255)
    - Conference on World Affairs, 1973 Mar. 12-16 (Box 255)
    - Gay News interview, Whitman book excerpt, 1976, undated (Box 255)
    - I Have More Fun With You Than Anybody reviews and clippings, 1972-1975 (Box 255)
    - Local News--Nichols/AIDS/Activist, 1986-1990 (Box 255)
    - Male Review review of Screw, undated (Box 255)
    - Men's liberation clippings and printed material, 1974-1994, undated (Box 255)
    - New York Times police article, 1990 Jan. 22 (Box 255)
    - Nichols/Clarke clipping book, 1972-1988, 3 folders (Box 255)
    - Nichols book reviews, 1972-2001, undated, 2 folders (Box 255)
    - Photo/clipping book, 1997-1998, undated, 1-3 of 4 folders (Box 255)
    - Photo/clipping book, 1997-1998, undated, 4 of 4 folders (Box 256)
    - Reviews and articles, 1974-2004, 2 folders (Box 256)
    - Screw cartoons, other clippings, 1969-1993, undated (Box 256)
    - Texas Gay Conference, 1981 Sept. (Box 256)
    - The Tomcat/Calamus Chronicles clipping book, 1991 Apr. 17-1992 July 22, 3 folders (Box 256)
    - The Tomcat Chronicles press material, 2004, undated (Box 256)
    - Various clippings and printed material, 1999, undated (Box 256)
  - Nichols Correspondence, 1952-2005 and undated, 10 boxes
    Consists of personal and business correspondence spanning the entirety of Nichols' adult life, with the bulk of the material dated between 1969 and 2000. Correspondence with other major figures in the early gay rights movement, including fellow Washington D.C. Mattachine Society founder Frank Kameny and Barbara Gittings, are included. While the political climate and need for action are often discussed in letters in this series, correspondence also covers topics of a more personal nature, including health, jobs, and Nichols' efforts to publish his literary work. Letters to and from friends and lovers, particularly Clarke and Logan Carter, are included as well. Additional major correspondents with Nichols include his mother Mary Finlayson Lund, Leo Skir, Bob Kunst, and James T. Sears. Early correspondence chronicles the work of Nichols and Lige Clarke as editors of the national newspaper Gay; later material documents Nichols' struggles to find agents and publishers for various manuscripts. Nichols' work as editor of the online publication Gay Today can be found in the writing and business correspondence grouping. Also included are a grouping of address and appointment books kept by Nichols. Series is predominantly organized by year, though groups of letters separated by Nichols are organized alphabetically by correspondent.
    - 1952-1965, 8 folders (Box 256)
    - 1966-1975, 16 folders (Box 257)
    - 1975-1991, 18 folders (Box 258)
    - 1992-1997, 11 folders (Box 259)
    - 1997-2003, 10 folders (Box 260)
    - 2003-2005, undated, 7 folders (Box 261)
    - Address and appointment books, 1986-1999, undated, 1-5 of 7 folders (Box 261)
    - Address and appointment books, 1986-1999, undated, 6-7 of 7 folders (Box 262)
    - Bush, Josef, 1989-1990, undated, 2 folders (Box 262)
    - Campbell, Louis J. (Nichols' biographer), 1998-2205, undated (Box 262)
    - Carter, Logan, 1976-1988, undated, 5 folders (Box 262)
    - Family letters, 1969-1981, 1-3 of 5 folders (Box 262)
    - Family letters, 1969-1981, 4-5 of 5 folders (Box 263)
    - From some close friends, 1982-1995, 2 folders (Box 263)
    - Good agents, 1994-1997 (Box 263)
    - Hargis, Rodney, 1986-1988, undated, 2 folders (Box 263)
    - Publisher correspondence, 1988-2004, 1-5 of 10 folders (Box 263)